Guide to the Adrian M. Srb papers, [ca.1947-1997]
Srb, Adrian M. papers, [ca. 1947-1997]
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Adrian M. Srb papers, [ca.1947-1997].
21-28-3159.
Adrian M. Srb.
7.3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, minutes, articles, records, lecture notes, exams, manuscripts, research material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Professional papers of Adrian M. Srb, geneticist and professor of plant breeding at Cornell.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Adrian Srb earned a bachelor's degree in English literature and a master's degree in agronomy from the University of Nebraska. He then earned a doctorate in biology in 1937 from Stanford University, where he taught until coming to Cornell in 1947 as an associate professor of plant breeding. He wrote numerous articles and papers on the genetics, physiology, and development of fungi, including the bread mold Neurospora and baker's yeast. At Cornell, he taught General Genetics, and authored the textbook General Genetics. He was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1941, and to the National Academy of Sciences in 1968. Born in 1917, Adrian Srb died in 1997.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Professional papers include correspondence with colleagues and students; class and course notes for general genetics and human genetics courses; research materials, including notes and charts relating to Neurospora; files relating to professional organizations, seminars, and conferences; files relating to activities at Cornell, particularly the creation of the Division of Biological Sciences; grant applications; and manuscripts for books.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Srb, Adrian M.; Cornell University. Faculty.; Cornell University. Division of Biological Sciences.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. Dept. of Plant Breeding.
Subjects:
Genetics.; Neurospora.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Box 1, Box 6
Series II. Course Material
Box 2, folders 1-18
Series III. Symposia, Seminars, Committee Material
Box 2, folders 19-42; Box 3, folders 1-24
Series IV. Projects and Subject Files
Box 3, folders 25-41; Box 4, folders 1-20, Box 7
Series V. Publications
Box 4, folders 21-37
Series VI. Grant Material
Box 4, folders 38-44
Series VII. Research Material
Box 4, folders 45-53 and Box 5
Series VIII. Recommendations
Box 6
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Anderson, William P. (recommendation), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Basl, Mary (correspondence), 1974-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bowen, Sam (correspondence), 1953-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Byrne, Barbara (correspondence), 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DeZeeuw, John (correspondence), 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Drozdowicz, Bronislaw (correspondence), 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Fortschritte der Botanik" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Geng, Anna (correspondence), 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Guterman, Sonia Kosow (correspondence), 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hartman, Zlata Dayton (correspondence), 1949-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Infanger, Sister Ann Martin (correspondence), 1959-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jarolmen, Howard (correspondence), 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Johnson, Jane (correspondence), 1959-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Johnson, Thomas (correspondence), 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Johnson, Tina (correspondence), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kasha, Ken (correspondence), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Keim, Wayne (correspondence), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Latterell, Richard (correspondence), 1954-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Leary, Jack (correspondence), 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lederberg, Seymour (correspondence), 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Levins, Richard (recommendation), 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Magill, Clint (correspondence), 1962-1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Magill, Jane Oates (correspondence), 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Moat, A.G. (correspondence), 1955-1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Muneta, Joan Leopold (correspondence), 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Murray, Jay (correspondence), 1954-1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Nasrallah, June (correspondence), 1970-1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Novak, Dennis (correspondence), 1965-1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Novak, Dennis (letters to editors), 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Poppa, Kenneth (correspondence), 1959-1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Phillips, Ronald (correspondence), 1965-1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Pincheiro, Guido (correspondence), 1963-1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Puhalla, John (correspondence), 1964-1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Reissig, Jose (correspondence), 1955-1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Sand, Seaward (correspondence), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Sandler, Laurence (correspondence), 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sanderson, Ken (correspondence), 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Schlottfeldt, Carlos (correspondence), 1949-1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Shaw, Margery Wayne, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Smith, Jimmie Bob (correspondence), 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Springer, Warren (correspondence), 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Steward, F.C.(correspondence), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Thompson, Sharron L. (correspondence), 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Topper, Violet M. (correspondence), 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Wall, Doris (correspondence), 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - White, B. Raynor (recommendation), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Williams, Antoinette (correspondence), 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Wolfner, Mariana (correspondence), 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Woodward, Val W. (correspondence), 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Woodward, Val W. (correspondence), 1958-1975 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - General correspondence (research related), 1947-1969 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - General correspondence, 1969-1985 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence- publications, 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - General correspondence and materials, 1967-1982 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Neurospora Research (correspondence), 1961-1980 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Permissions for Publication (correspondence), 1949-1972 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Pre-publication correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Prospective student- correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - General Genetics (textbook)- correspondence (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-Confidential, 1969-1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence-Personal Items, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - A.D. White Professors-at-Large: McClintock Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Basl, Mary: Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Basl, Mary: Laboratory Matters (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Bonner, David M. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Brown, Robert E. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Department of H.E.W. Certificate, 1951-1982 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Ephrussi, Boris (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - General Genetics(by Srb and Owen) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Genetics and Development-Correspondence and Memos (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Keeton Chair (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Littlewood, Roland (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Russell, Peter (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Steward, F.C. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - University of Nebraska (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Series II. Course Material
  - Human Genetics- lecture notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Human Genetics 282, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Plant Breeding 101 and 201 (exams), 1948-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Course Notes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Research Notes and Materials (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Class Notes, 1940's (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Neurospora Research (random unsorted materials) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Tetrad Analyses (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ascospore work from Srb's lab (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Negatives for plates (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rollins/Adams/Emerson materials (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Charts and Materials (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Evolution of Manuscripts and Research Proposals, 1969-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Seminars and lectures, 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - California Tech., 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lecture for French Genetics Society, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Lecture at Hamilton College, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series III. Symposia, Seminars, Committee Material
  - Rockefeller Conference on Extra-Chromosomal Heredity (Gif-sur-Yvette), 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sabbatical, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Seminars and lectures, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Symposium- SUNY Albany, Feb. 8, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Visiting Lectures, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sabbatical- University of Edinburgh, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Seminars, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - La Jolla Conference in California, Feb. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Brookhaven Symposium, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Seminars- Arginine Metabolism (Stanford University) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - American Society of Naturalists, 1949-1957 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sigma Xi, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - National Poultry Breeders' Roundtable, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Biology Visiting Committee- Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1954-1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Committee on Academic Work and Interest, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Presidential Screening Committee, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Biological Sciences Coordinating Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Cornell Council, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Vicious Circle, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Committee on Systematics, Evolution, and Environmental Biology, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - President's Committee on Biological Sciences, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Interim Executive Committee on Biology, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Subcommittee on preliminary definitions of new positions to be created in biology, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Recruitment to the Division of Biology, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee- Division of Biological Sciences, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ultrastructure Search Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ad Hoc Committees- Appointments and Tenure, 1966-1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Genetics Search Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Botanical Society of Edinburgh (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Biology Colloquium, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General Committee of the Graduate School, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Developmental Biologist Search Committee, 1970-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Institutes of Health- Training Committee, 1969-1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Mycological Congress- University of Glasgow, Sept. 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - MSU/AEC Visiting Committee, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Professors-at-Large Selection Committee, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Search Committee for Director- Biological Sciences, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Ad Hoc Grievance Committee, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Guggenheim Educational Advisory Board, 1975-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Physiology Chairman- Search Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Recombinant DNA Committee, Feb. 1976- July 1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Recombinant DNA Committee, Aug. 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jacob Gould Schurman Professorship, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Criteria for Promotions" Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Search Committee for Dean- College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Boyce-Thompson Search Committee, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Series IV. Projects and Subject Files
  - Guggenheim Application, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Book Collection Contest (Arthur H. Dean and Mary Marden Dean), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Report to Nutrition Foundation, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - White Memorial, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Rockefeller Project- Article No. 17, 1959-1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - National Science Foundation- Undergraduate Teaching Proposal, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - National Science Foundation Postdoctoral Fellowship- France, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1966-1983 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - National Institutes of Health (Genetics Training Committee Award) (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - National Institutes of Health, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - National Institute of General Medical Sciences- National Institutes of Health (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Russian Genetics (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Cornell University Press, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Fulbright Act, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Edgerton Career Teaching Award, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Retirement, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Biology Center, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Site visit- MSU/AEC Lab, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - University of Nebraska- Master's Program, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - University of Western Ontario, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Liberty Hyde Bailey Professorships, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chile Trip, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 75th Anniversary of the Department of Plant Breeding- synopsis, symposium, invitations, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Biotechnology Institute, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Genetics Study Session, 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Graduate Field Of Genetics, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Graduate Field of Genetics, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - College of Arts and Sciences- membership, 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Section of Genetics, Development, and Physiology- correspondences, 1965-1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Division Director- Biological Sciences, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Division of Biological Sciences, 1963-1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Project Reports, 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - College Research Reports (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Progress Reports for Grants, 1950-1969 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Health Careers, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - A.D. White Professorship, Committee (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Biography: Adrian M. Srb (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Biological Science 280, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Biology Division Plans, etc. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Class Notes and Graduate Days at Stanford (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - College and University Fiscal Procedures (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Developmental Biology-Search Committee (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Early Research (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Genes and the Chemistry of the Organism by G.w. Beadle (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Haman Genetics: Bibliographies (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Mann Library Board, Committee (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - National Academy of Sciences, Nominating Committee (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - National Institues of Health on Graduate Training and Genetics Training (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - National Science Foundation-Cali, Columbia Symposium (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Neurospora Newsletter, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings-Human Heredity and Other Genetics Subjects (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Notes: Genetics and Human Welfare (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Pre-doc and post-doc: Research Notes (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Professor R.P. Murphy's File on A. Srb, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Recombinant DNA, Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Round Spore Mutants at Neurosporo (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Routine Questions (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Sabbatical, Laboratory Matters, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Tenth International Botanical Congress, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Treatise-Steward (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Series V. Publications
  - Paper for Plant Physiology- implications of genetics for growth and development, 1957-1968 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Health News article, Dec. 1958 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Encyclopedia of Science and Technology, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "Genes and Metabolic Pathways" (paper)- Harper & Row, publishers, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - "Genes and Metabolic Pathways" (paper)- Harper & Row, publishers, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Dictionary of American Biography (Rollins/Adams/Emerson), 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - "... Canavanine Resistance in Yeast" (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - "Mutation and Selection in Fungi"- paper written by Srb (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "The Urgency of Graduate Education"- lecture (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Unpublished Srb and Basl paper (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "Cytoplasmic Inheritance" & "Selection Models"-papers (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Neurospora Newsletter #20- "Festschrift", 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Review of Russell & Srb's paper, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Random published articles written by Srb (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Curriculum Vitae-Adrian Morris Srb (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Nasrallah and Srb (PNAS), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Resolutions- Lowell F. Randolph's retirement and death, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous Information (unsorted) (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Series VI. Grant Material
  - Grant applications (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Grant applications (continued) (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Grant applications (continued) (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Grant correspondence (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Grant materials- unsorted (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences- unsorted correspondence (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Publication Purchases, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Series VII. Research Material
  - Growth Decay folder (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Cavenery folder (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Peak Complementation folder (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Book I (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Book II (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Book III (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Book IV (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Neurospora growth rates in tubes (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks of research (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Bound binder of Neurospora research (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Binder V (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Binder VI (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Binder VII (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Binder VIII (Box 5, Folder 5)
    The rest of this box contains miscellaneous notebooks consisting of charts, graphs, diagrams and observations Srb made during his years of research.
- Series VIII. Recommendations
  - Student Recommendations- correspondence (unsorted) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Student Recommendations- correspondence (unsorted) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Student Recommendations- correspondence (unsorted) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Student Recommendations- correspondence (unsorted) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Student Recommendations- correspondence (unsorted) (Box 6, Folder 5)